

# \_ouis Lippens

Ghent University (FEB), Sint-Pietersplein 6, 9000 Gent, Belgium

☑ Louis.Lippens@UGent.be | 备 louislippens.be | ☑ Louis-Lippens | ☑ lglip | 🛅 louislippens

#### About Me

I am a joint PhD researcher in labour economics and sociology of labour at Ghent University and Vrije Universiteit Brussel with an interdisciplinary background and a pronounced interest in data visualisation. My present work focuses on the determinants of and contextual factors contributing to (ethnic) hiring discrimination. More broadly, I research labour market topics relating to hiring and selection and labour demand and supply. I have previously worked for consulting firms on data governance, data analytics, and HR projects. I have also obtained a master's degree in work psychology and a business degree in general management.

## **Employment**

## ACADEMIA (FULL-TIME)

**Ghent University** Ghent RF

Aug. 2019 - Present DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- · Research on topics in labour economics, contributing to solving societal questions surrounding the (Belgian) labour market
- · Teaching assignments, including guiding last-year students with their master's thesis, coaching bachelor students on migration research topics, and giving guest lectures on economic research
- · Development of low-threshold, interactive, and flexible tools (e.g. multicultural situational judgment tests) to increase the awareness of HR professionals' intercultural competence and to empower them to deal with the drivers of their competence
- · Dissertation: research on (ethnic) hiring discrimination, its determinants, its mechanisms, and the influence of the organisational context

Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels, BE

VISITING DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Aug. 2019 - Present

· Research on topics in sociology of labour

## PRIVATE SECTOR (FULL-TIME)

**BDO** Ghent/Antwerp/Brussels, BE

SENIOR CONSULTANT (DATA ANALYTICS)

Oct. 2018 - Jul. 2019

- · Performed survey research on the modal shift in transportation and developed a predictive model for a governmental body and an inland port
- · Advised a private company active in the entertainment industry on the design of a data asset repository
- Constructed a financial model for a mid-scale mobility management project

**Capgemini Invent** Brussels, BE

CONSULTANT (DATA GOVERNANCE)

Sep. 2017 - Sep. 2018

May 2017 - Jun. 2017

Sep. 2015 - Jan. 2016

- · Performed a benchmark study of data governance operating models in financial services
- · Developed and optimised various data asset documentation processes in the context of BCBS239 and GDPR regulatory frameworks
- Conducted a data quality maturity assessment across various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank
- Set up data-sharing agreements between various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank

#### INTERNSHIPS (FULL-TIME)

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

**CEMAC** Ghent, BE

Redesign of the firm's organisational structure and internal business processes

Analysis of the firm's product strategy and internationalisation opportunities and capabilities

The Future Alliance Ghent. BE

HR CONSULTANT

- Organised assessment and development centres for middle management candidates
- Organised workshops concerning HR-related topics (e.g. giving and receiving feedback)
- · Carried out recruitment and selection assignments for entry and (middle) management functions

Hudson Ghent, BE

HR CONSULTANT Oct. 2014 - Nov. 2014

Developed 40 rating scales, including a manual, for the advisory firm's dedicated competency model

#### SOCIAL SECTOR (PART-TIME)

**180 Degrees Consulting** Ghent BF

HR DIRECTOR

- 180 Degrees Consulting (180DC) is the world's largest international consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises
- Led the human capital activities of 180DC's Ghent University branch
- · Conducted selection tests, incl. reasoning tests and structured interviews, of about 70 university students
- Other activities: implementation of 180° feedback system, social media marketing, event support

**180 Degrees Consulting** Ghent, BE

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

- · Co-developed an integrated fundraising and marketing strategy for the NGO 'Join For Water'
- Conducted survey research regarding the brand perceptions of Join For Water's donors and sympathizers
- · Developed an evidence-based, bespoke brand personality for Join For Water, as well as brand improvement guidelines

## **Education**

**Ghent University** Ghent RF

PhD, Economics Aug. 2019 - Present

- Doctoral courses: Econometrics, Advanced Econometrics (Non-Linear Techniques), Labour Economics, Multilevel Analysis
- Other courses: Advanced Academic Writing in English, Multilevel Analysis in R, Generalised Linear Models in R, Multidisciplinary Research Tools to Study Work and the Labour Market, Effective Graphical Displays
- · Supervisors: Prof. Stijn Baert, Prof. Eva Derous

Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels, BE

Aug. 2019 - Present PhD. Sociology

- · Supervisor: Prof. Pieter-Paul Verhaeghe
- Joint PhD with Ghent University as the main institution

**Vlerick Business School** Ghent, BE

MM, GENERAL MANAGEMENT (MAGNA CUM LAUDE)

Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2017

Jul. 2015 - Jun. 2016

Mar. 2015 - Jun. 2015

- · Key Courses: Corporate Finance, Financial Accounting, Management Accounting and Control, Strategic Management, Operations Management
- Electives: Big Data and Data Analytics, Digital Strategy (w/BNPP Fortis), Strategy and Organisational Design, Mergers and Acquisitions (w/Gimv)
- Bootcamp: Strategic Innovation in Renewable Energy (w/ Durabilis)

**Ghent University** Ghent. BE

MSc, Industrial and Organisational Psychology (Magna Cum Laude)

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2016

- · Key Courses: Multi-level Organisational Research, Statistics, Applied Data Analysis, Human Resource Management, Industrial Relations
- Master's thesis: Short form of the Wilde Intelligenztest: Psychometric qualities and utility of a 12-minute intelligence test for personnel selection

## **Publications**

## **TECHNICAL REPORTS**

2022 **Ghent University** 

Inactiviteit in Europa en de Belgische gewesten

S Baert, L Lippens

**Ghent University** 2022

Inactiviteit onder migranten in België

S Baert, E Derous, B George, L Lippens, G Van Hoye, B Neyt, S Van Hoof

**Ghent University** 2022

Welzijn op het werk in Vlaanderen

S Baert, E Clays, E Derous, K du Bois, L Lippens, S Mertens, B Neyt, ...

2021 **Ghent University** 

Discriminatie op de Gentse arbeidsmarkt anno 2021: rapportering

S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait

2021 **Ghent University** 

Nulmeting discriminatie op de Antwerpse arbeidsmarkt: rapportering

S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait, A Sharipova

#### **DISCUSSION PAPERS**

#### 2021 IZA Institute of Labour Economics

The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments L Lippens, S Vermeiren, S Baert

#### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

#### 2022 Applied Economics Letters

Ethnic discrimination on paper: Uncovering realtors' willingness to discriminate with mystery mails

A Ghekiere, L Lippens, S Baert, PP Verhaeghe

# Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies

Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics? A systematic review of the empirical evidence

L Lippens, S Baert, A Ghekiere, PP Verhaeghe, E Derous

#### 2021 **Economics Letters**

Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment

L Lippens, S Baert, E Derous

#### 2021 PLOS ONE

How do employees think the COVID-19 crisis will affect their careers?

L Lippens, E Moens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

#### 2021 The European Journal of Health Economics

The COVID-19 crisis and telework: A research survey on experiences, expectations and hopes

E Moens, L Lippens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

Visit my Google Scholar profile at https://bit.ly/louis-lippens-scholar for a comprehensive overview of my research.

## Services and Outreach \_\_\_\_\_

#### PEER REVIEWS

In addition to conducting my own research, I have also reviewed the work of some of my peers. I have served as a reviewer (ad hoc) for the Journal of Labor Economics (1), Work and Occupations (1), Social Science & Medicine (1), Social Forces (1), Journal of Sociology (1) PLOS ONE (2), International Migration Review (1), Social Policy and Society (1), Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics (1), International Journal of Manpower (1), and Economics Bulletin (2).

#### ACADEMIC OUTREACH

......

Oslo, NO	2022 IMISCOE Annual Conference	2022
0510, 110	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	
Orléans, FR	Spring Meeting of Young Economists	2022
Oneuns, FR	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	
Ghent, BE	CESSMIR PhD Meeting	2021
GHEIR, DE	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	
Barcelona, ES	2021 EALE Annual Conference	2021
(online)	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	
Utrecht, NL	Day of Sociology	2021
(online)	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	
Ghent, BE	CESSMIR Research Day	2021
GHEIR, DL	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	
Ghent, BE	Faculty of Economics and Business Administration Research Day	2021
GHEHL, DL	Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment	
Brussels, BE	2020 Context Matters Symposium	2020
Diussels, DE	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	

## SOCIETAL OUTREACH

2022	UGent @ Work	Story
	Well-being at work in Flanders (Belgium): New figures interpreted based on previous research	Story
2022	UGent @ Work	Blog post
	Ethnic labour market discrimination: Generalisation or aversion?	Blog post
2022	HR Magazine	Magazine article
	Structured interview best predicts a good match	Magazine article
2022	UGent @ Work	Story
	Inactivity among migrants in Belgium	Story
2022	UGent @ Work	Story
	Inactivity in Europe and the Belgian Regions	Story
2022	LinkedIn	Blog post
	The top-ranked selection tools to hire the best-performing candidate	Blog post
2021	Het Laatste Nieuws	Newspaper article
	Older applicants face greater hiring discrimination than ethnic minority applicants worldwide	rvewspaper article
2021	Trends (magazine)	Newspaper article
	Hiring discrimination based on age is worse than ethnic hiring discrimination	rvewspaper article
2021	UGent @ Work	Blog post
	Does discrimination have a price?	Biog post
2021	Radio 1, Nieuwe Feiten	Radio interview
	Does discrimination have a price?	radio interview
2020	Apache	Newspaper article
	Trainings against labour market discrimination	wewspaper article
2020	Het Laatste Nieuws	
	My job disappears, my pay gets smaller, my promotion gets snubbed: This is how the Flemish people think	Newspaper article
	about their work future	

# Skills\_\_\_\_\_

## GENERAL SKILLS

Research	Analytics	Business
Audit studies – Survey research – Experimental research – Applied psychometrics	(Ordered) logit models – Linear models – Meta-analysis – Meta-regression – Reliability and validity analysis – Structural equation modeling	Project management – Human capital management – Corporate finance – Consultancy

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Coding Languages	Research Software	<b>Business Software</b>	Creative Software	Other
R (ggplot2, tidyverse, hugo, xaringan, quarto) – SQL	RStudio – Stata – SPSS – Knime	Collibra – MS Office	Photoshop – GIMP – Ableton Live	Git – Markdown – LaTeX

## LANGUAGES

Skill	Dutch	English	French
Reading	C2	C2	C1
Writing	C2	C2	B1
Listening	C2	C2	B2
Speaking	C2	C1	B1

Note. CEFR: A1/A2: Basic User; B1/B2: Independent User; C1/C2: Proficient User.

## Certificates

2019	Exploratory Data Analysis (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2018	Reproducible Research (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2019	R Programming (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2017	Financial Markets (Yale University)	Coursera
2017	Fundamentals of Quantitative Modeling (Wharton School)	Coursera
2017 2017	Collibra Community Manager Collibra Data Steward	Collibra Collibra

## **Honors and Awards**

#### 2017 Student Achievement for Outstanding Performance

Personal recognition for obtaining the most and highest positive peer evaluations in group assignments throughout the academic year.

Vlerick Business School

#### 2015 Best European Consulting Branch

180 Degrees Consulting Ghent was named the best overall European branch (Europe) of the world's largest consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises. We were lauded for our collaboration-fostering spirit, high client focus and professional approach to private partnerships.

180 Degrees Consulting

## Trivia

#### Sucker for R

I am a sucker for everything related to R (ggplot2, Shiny, Xaringan...), my go-to environment for statistical computing. The content of this very resume is written in R, using R Markdown, the {{vitae}} package, and some LaTeX typesetting.

#### Passionate about electronic music

I have been playing the piano since I was 9 years old, albeit much less frequently in the past few years. Moreover, between the ages of 15 and 22, I was active as an electronic music artist, producer, and event manager.

#### Fond of the sea

As a teenager, I longed to spend my summer vacations at the seaside. From my 18th birthday onwards, after an intensive year of training, I was able to combine this fondness for the sea with a student job as a lifeguard at the Belgian coast for 6 consecutive summers.